Created By befirelast@pt.sjtu
Created time 11.09.17 14:06:35
★★★翻译者：flyinglisa★★★
★★★时间轴调整：befirelast@pt.sjtu★★★
我说不出是什么使我爱上越南
Ican't say what made me fall in love with Vietnam.
因为这的女人声音使人迷醉?
That a woman's voice can drug you?
因为这的一切都很热情?
That everything is so intense -
颜色
the colours,
气味
the taste,
甚至这儿的雨?
even the rain?
这儿的雨可不像伦敦那可恶的雨
Nothing like the filthy rain in London.
片名: 安静的美国人
越南西贡,1952 人们说不管你寻求什么
They say whatever you're looking for
你都能在这儿如愿以偿
you will find here.
人们说来到越南
They say you come to Vietnam
你能立刻明白很多事
and you understand a lot in a few minutes.
剩下的你得自己去经历
But the rest has got to be lived.
首先是气味 -
The smell, that's the first thing that hits you -
预示着你用灵魂交换的一切
promising everything in exchange for your soul.
然后是热天气
And the heat.
你的衣服马上变得不像样
Your shirt is straight away a rag.
你会记不起自己的名字
You can hardly remember your name,
或是你来这是逃避什么的
or what you came to escape from.
不过在晚上,这儿凉风悉悉
But at night, there's a breeze.
这的河美极了
The river is beautiful.
没有战争,那些枪声只是烟花
You could be forgiven for thinking there was no war,
这些自欺欺人的想法都会被谅解
that the gunshots were fireworks,
只有享乐最重要
that only pleasure matters.
抽斗鸦片
A pipe of opium,
或抚摸那说爱你的女人
or the touch of a girl who might tell you she loves you.
然而有些事还是发生了
And then something happens,
你知道那会发生
as you knew it would,
然后一切都改变了
and nothing can ever be the same again.
福勒先生
Monsieur Fowler.
感谢你亲自过来
Thank you for coming in.
很抱歉这时候打挠你
I'm sorry to ask you at this hour.
我知道的不比你多
I know about as much as you do.
他是美国人,大约30岁
He's an American. He's about 30.
他为经济援助团工作
He works for the Economic Aid Mission.
我喜欢他
And I like him.
他是个不错的小伙子,说真的
He's a very good chap. Serious.
不像其他欧洲饭店里吵闹的混球
Not like those noisy bastards down at the Continental.
他很安静
He's a quiet American.
是的,一个非常安静的美国人
Yes. A very quiet American.
他死了,是吗?
He's dead, isn't he?
不是做贼心虚 我只是根据事实推测
Not guilty. I just put two and two together.
他被刀捅死的
He was killed by a knife.
你能辨认出他吗?
Can you identify him?
是的
Yes.
他是...我的朋友
He was... a friend.
老实说我并不怎么为他悲哀
To tell you the truth, I'm not completely sorry.
这些美国人给我们惹了不少麻烦
These Americans are causing a lot of trouble to us.
不过这始终是凶杀案
But still, a murder is a murder.
能提供什么线索吗?
Anything to help us?
没有
No.
一点线索也没
Nothing at all.
那请吧
Please.
派尔...
Pyle...
他死了
est mort.
被暗杀了
Assassinated.
怎么死的?
How?
被刀捅死的
He was stabbed.
是的
Yes.
他很爱我
He was in love with me.
是的,的确
Yes. He was.
我很抱歉,凤
I'm so sorry, Phuong.
我回我妈那儿
I go to my mother's.
我得静一静
I must think.
我是在欧洲旅馆里见到派尔的 -
I met Pyle where you meet everybody -
在那儿你能遇到很多人
at the Hotel Continental.
我每天上午11点都会在那儿
I'm there every morning at 1 1. 00.
我是英国人,我有去喝茶的习惯
I'm English. I have habits. I drink tea.
我是个记者,所以听听小道消息
I'm a reporter, so I listen.
我有个情人 我喜欢看着她和朋友走进饮料吧
I have a lover. I like to watch her arrive at the milk bar.
我在那看到艾登.派尔
And there was Alden Pyle.
看到他年青正直的脸
A face with no history and no problems.
我们都曾有过这样一张脸
The face we all had once.
- 我叫艾登.派尔 -我叫托马斯.福勒
- I'm Alden Pyle. - I'm Thomas Fowler.
- 你是伦敦时报的 - 你知道很多嘛
- The London Times. - You've done your homework.
我读过你的文章
I've read your articles.
- 我能坐这吗? - 请
- May I join you? - Please.
你来西贡做什么,派尔先生?
And what brings you to Saigon, Mr Pyle?
我是经济援助团的 负责医疗方面
I'm with the Economic Aid Mission, on the medical side.
眼疾.你知道沙眼吗? 这病在这很普遍,实事上很容易治
Eye disease. Do know trachoma? It's very common here. Very easy to treat.
- 你住在旅店? - 只是顺便过来喝杯茶
- Are you staying at the hotel? - No. I just dropped by for tea.
我要经过这去上班
On the way to the office.
能见到你真是意外的好运
This is really a stroke of luck for me.
你是少数几个...
You're one of the few correspondents
能深入战场了解事实真相的通讯员之一
who goes out into the field to see what's happening.
不再是了. 而且我不认为自己是通讯员
Not any more. Besides, I have never thought of myself as a correspondent.
我只是个记者,我没有自己的观点
I'm just a reporter. I offer no point of view.
我不采取行动 也不参与行动
I take no action. I don't get involved.
我只是报道我所看到的
I just report what I see.
- 但是你总有想法吧 - 就算想法也是一种行动.
- But you must have an opinion. - Even an opinion is a form of action.
我还是...
Still, I'd appreciate...
派尔渴望知道越南的一切
Pyle was hungry for everything I could tell him about Vietnam
越南的独立战争
and her fight for independence.
为什么法国人打了败仗?
Why were the French losing the war?
为什么共产党赢了?
And why were the communists winning?
然后他见到凤
Then he saw Phuong.
我当时就该意识到对派尔这样的人而言
I should have realised how saving a country and saving a woman
拯救一个女子和拯救一个国家一样重要
could be the same thing to someone like Pyle.
我们得遏制共产主义
We've got to contain communism.
我们能做到
What could be done, what should be done,
他的思想,他读的书
what he thought, what he'd read.
他使我记起
He made me remember there was a time
曾经我也有远大抱负
when I had wanted to make a difference.
- 就这么看着他们失去自由吗? - "自由" 是个西式词语
- T o watch liberty snuffed out? - "Liberty" is a western word.
你认为越南人的自由是什么?
How do you define it for the Vietnamese?
自由选择权
The freedom to choose.
你给他们选择权 他们会投票选胡志明
OK, you give them that, they vote and they elect Ho Chi Minh.
事实往往比它看起来要复杂
Things are more complicated than they seem.
- 那是什么? -手榴弹
- What was that? - A grenade.
- 听上去像汽车逆火 - 在这呆一个星期,你就能听出不同来
- It sounded like a car backfiring. - A week here, you'll know the difference.
见到你真的很高兴
It's been a genuine pleasure meeting you.
- 也许我们能一起吃个饭 - 我很期待
- Maybe we could eat dinner. - I look forward to it.
好极了
Great.
早安
Good morning.
早安,辛.有什么新闻吗?
Morning, Hinh. Anything new?
腐败,造假...
Oh, corruption, mendacity...
我说了"新"闻
I said new.
有谣言说...
There is a rumour that the communists
共产党计划要袭击北部的Phat Diem.
are planning an attack in the north, at Phat Diem.
你的线人说的?
One of your contacts?
是的,先生
Yes, sir.
你的电报
And a telegram.
- 伦敦办事处发来的 - 史达明先生
- From the London office. - Mr Stemins.
他说报社回顾了外国办事处的情况
He says the paper has conducted a review of the foreign desk.
他想要你回伦敦
He wants you based in London.
天啊
Christ.
我以为你喜欢伦敦,先生
I thought you liked London, sir.
我是喜欢,但只是喜欢那个地理位置 不是该死的去那儿
I do, but I like it just where it is. I don't want to bloody go there.
为什么? 办事处差事?
For what? A desk job?
也许他们认为...
They probably think it's cheaper
让通讯社覆盖越南会更便宜
to let the wire services cover Vietnam.
我们一共交过几篇报道?
How many stories have we given them?
今年内?
This year?
- 是的 - 三篇
- Yes. - Three.
噢,该死
Oh, shit.
也许...我该去那儿
Maybe... I should go up there.
- 哪儿,先生? - Phat Diem.
- Where, sir? - Phat Diem.
那地方可不容易进 共产党正在攻打那儿
It's not an easy place to get into, with the communist attack.
给史达明发个电报
Send a cable to Stemins.
了解你目前的顾虑.句号
Understand your current concern. Stop.
正在写一篇重要的报道.句号
Am working on a story of major proportions. Stop.
要求留下直到写完.句号
Suggest I remain in Saigon until completed. Stop.
福勒
Fowler.
什么重要的报道,先生?
Which story is that, sir?
我不知道
I don't know.
但我知道你一定认得什么人 能把我弄进那地方
But I'm sure you know someone who can get me in there.
今天是我们的周年纪念 你不记得了?
Today our anniversary. Did you forget?
这么快就两年了?
Can it be two years already?
- 是的 - 是的?
- Yes. - Yes?
小心点.我老了,很脆弱
Be careful with me. I'm old and fragile.
没那么老
Not so old.
也没那么脆弱
Not so fragile.
托马斯!
Tom!
托马斯.
Thomas.
- 你好 - 你好
- Hello. - Hello again.
我和一些朋友一起 介意和我们一块吗?
I'm here with some friends. Care to join us?
- 凤,这是派尔先生. - 艾登,请
- Phuong, this is Mr Pyle. - Alden, please.
很高兴见到你
请原谅我的法语说得不好
认识乔.滕尼吗? 是美国公使馆的
You know Joe Tunney, from the American legation.
是的,我认识乔 最近又颠覆了什么小国了吗?
Yes, I know Joe. Overthrown any small countries recently?
- 福勒到处都有同谋 - 没错
- Fowler sees conspiracies everywhere. - That's for sure.
共产党真的要攻打Phat Diem吗?
Is it true that the communists are attacking Phat Diem?
我他妈怎么知道? 我们只报道胜利
How the fuck should I know? We only report victories.
我们有队医疗小组 不被允许经过金边
One of our medical teams wasn't allowed past Phnom Penh.
- 我正想去那儿呢 - 那是个天主教城镇,是吗?
- I was thinking of going up there. - It's a Catholic town, isn't it?
- 你今晚有约会吗?
- You got a date tonight? - Bill...
她每晚都有约会
She's got a date every night.
你有你的女人了,我想要我的
You got your piece of ass. I want mine.
派尔,小伙子们, 我们去500女孩之家吧
Pyle, fellas, let's go to the House of 500 Girls.
不,谢了
Oh, no thanks.
- 我本该带他们去吃饭 - 我们已在 Arc en Ciel订了位子
- I was planning on taking them to dinner. - We've already booked at the Arc en Ciel.
那很好 你们在那吃
That's great. You go eat at the L'Arc en Ciel
我在隔壁吃
and I'll get eaten next door.
听上去不错 来吧,比尔
Sounds like a plan. Come on, Bill.
跟我走
Walk with me.
看上去是个不错的年青人
Seems like a nice young man.
- 他干什么的? - 医疗援助什么的
- What does he do? - Something with medical aid.
你先去占张桌子 我去拯救我们的派尔先生
You go and get us a table and I'll go and rescue our Mr Pyle.
谢谢
Thank you.
我不进去,我只是送他来
I'm not staying. Just dropping him off.
派尔,快过来
Pyle! Let's get out of here.
抱着她
Put your arm around this one.
他们以为你已经挑了个姑娘 就不会缠着你了
If they think you've chosen one, they'll let you go.
抱着她
Put your arm around her.
- 晚安,格里吉! - 谁最想要这钱?
- Night, Granger! - Who wants the money most?
凤小姐,很抱歉让你久等
Miss Phuong, please forgive us for keeping you waiting.
我原谅你
I forgive you.
- 我们不得不看看比尔是不是到家了 - 家!
- We had to make sure Bill got home. - Home!
- 30号? - 什么?
- Number 30? - Sorry?
舞小姐的票 你买张票跳一支舞
Tickets for the taxi dancers. You buy a ticket for a dance.
买张吧.也许我会陪你跳
Buy a ticket. Maybe I dance with you.
给你
There you are.
能请你吗?
Shall we?
凤是个很美的名字
Phuong is a very beautiful name.
是凤凰的意思
It mean phoenix.
我以为是花的意思 就像你头上戴的
I thought it meant flower. Like the ones in your hair.
你喜欢我的发式吗?
Do you like my hair?
- 这是传统发式 - 很漂亮
- This is traditional style. - It's very nice.
- 会说越南语吗? - 当然.考我吧
- Do you know Vietnamese? - Sure. Try me.
你跳舞时不要带领舞伴
不,我不会...
No. I don't...
我只知道两个词
I only know two words.
- 福勒先生 - 你好
- Mr Fowler. - Hello.
- 我能坐下吗? - 当然
- May l? - Of course.
谢谢
Thanks.
好久不见了
Haven't seen you for a long time.
- 我常不在这 - 是的
- I'm away a lot. - Yes.
他是谁?你朋友?
Who's he? Your friend?
他叫派尔 他是美国经济使团的
His name is Pyle. He's with the American Economic Mission.
他来自波斯顿,美国
He's from Boston. In America.
他跳得很烂
He's a very bad dancer.
是的
Yes.
- 他结婚了吗? - 据我所知没有
- He is married? - Not that I know of, no.
这是凤的姐姐 艾登.派尔
This is Phuong's sister. Alden Pyle.
很高兴见到你
Very happy to meet you.
你父亲是商人?
Your father is a business man?
不,他是教授
No. He's a professor.
我妹妹舞跳得很好,对吗?
My sister is very good dancer, yes?
- 比我好多了 - 她是我唯一的妹妹
- She's too good for me. - She's my only sister.
他很可爱,是美国人 还很有钱
有时你和你所讨厌的法国人 一样那么粗俗
你妹妹很漂亮
Your sister's a very pretty girl.
我妹妹是西贡最漂亮的女孩
My sister is the most beautiful girl in Saigon.
我绝对相信 福勒先生是个非常幸运的男人
I don't doubt that at all. Mr Fowler's a very lucky man.
我父亲因为没有孙子非常难过
My father was very sad he had no grandchildren.
想喝点什么吗?
Would you like a drink?
不,谢谢
No. Thank you.
我朋友在那儿
My friends.
真高兴见到你 期望很快能再面
So pleased to have met you. I hope we meet again soon.
- 也许你能安排一下 - 等我从北部回来吧
- Perhaps you could arrange. - When I get back from the north.
你要去北部?
You are going north?
是的
Yes.
那你一定要和我及我妹妹吃午饭
Then you must come and have dinner
当福勒先生不在时
with me and my sister when Mr Fowler is gone.
- 让她高兴高兴 - 谢谢,我很想去
- To cheer her up. - Thank you. I'd like that very much.
- 多好的女子 - 绝对的圣人
- What a nice woman. - Absolute saint.
她以前在进出口办事处工作
She used to work in office. Import-export.
- 真的吗? - 她会速记
- Really? - She knows shorthand.
- 是吗? - 也许你那需要人
- Does she? - Maybe you need someone.
也许能想想办法
Maybe we could work something out.
请原谅我和凤小姐跳了那么多次舞
Please forgive me for dancing with Miss Phuong so many times.
- 我喜欢看她跳舞 - 她跳得真好
- I like watching her dance. - She's a very good dancer.
那是当然 她以前靠跳舞吃饭呢
She should be. She used to do it for a living.
- 什么意思? - 她以前是舞小姐
- What do you mean? - She was a taxi dancer.
舞女,就在 Arc en Ciel.
A hostess. Here at the Arc en Ciel.
我以为你说她是来自好人家的
I thought you said she came from a good family.
是啊,但他父亲死了 所以姐妹俩得自己讨生活
She did, but the father died so the sisters had to earn a living.
- 噢,那太糟了 - 什么?
- Well, that's too bad. - What?
那不是只比街上那些女子好一点点?
Isn't that just a step up from the girls across the street?
天啊,不 我等了六个月才约到她
Good God, no. It took me six months to get her to go on a date.
手榴弹
Grenade.
- 那你结婚了吗? - 是的
- So are you married? - Yes, I am.
但不是和她
But not to her.
有件事我还没和你说
There's something I haven't told you.
总部来了电报,叫我回伦敦
I got a telegram from the paper, asking me to go back to London.
那你会走吗?
So will you go?
我给他们回了电报
I've cabled them,
请求让我留下,但是...
asking them to let me stay, but...
如果他们不付我薪水
if they stop paying me,
我不知道我们该怎么生活
I'm not sure how we'll live.
我和你一起回伦敦
I come with you to London.
如果可以我一定跟你结婚
I'd marry you if I could.
- 你知道的这点 - 是的
- You know that. - Yes.
我总是这么跟我姐姐说的
That's what I always tell my sister.
你觉得你妻子肯离婚吗?
You think your wife will give divorce?
我不知道
I doubt it.
一切从什么时候开始改变的?
When did everything change?
也许不是一朝一夕的事
Maybe there isn't one moment.
招我回伦敦的电报?
The cable from London calling me home?
或盯着他们一起跳舞?
Or watching them dancing together?
或是接下来我和她之间的...
Or what followed between us, she and I,
漫漫长夜?
through the long night?
我从没勇敢过
I was never brave.
但我还是去了北部
But there I was, heading north,
失去凤的恐惧...
the fear of losing Phuong more terrifying
要大过挨子弹的恐惧
than the fear of any bullet.
共产党人4天前袭击了这里
The communists attacked four days ago.
到昨天才被我们击退
We pushed them back only yesterday.
我们认为还有300人在村里
We think there is 300 in this village.
- 但你看不到他们 - 情况越来越糟了,是吗?
- But you will not see them. - It's getting worse, isn't it?
你们还能维持多久?
How long can you keep going?
几个月,也许
A few months, maybe.
我的手下都在数着子弹打
My men are counting bullets.
不,不!别开枪!
No, no! Don't shoot!
你来这干嘛?
What the hell are you doing here?
他们不让我的车开过金边
They wouldn't let my truck out of Phnom Penh
我只好设法自个过来
so I figured I'd see what was going on for myself.
你能活着来到这真是幸运
You're lucky to get here alive.
我弄到船后事情就不难了 这不贵
It wasn't that hard after I hired a boat. It wasn't expensive.
- 最后我干脆买下它 - 你疯了
- In the end I just bought it. - You are mad.
- 我疯了? - 是的
- I'm mad? - Yes.
你有没有看到谁得了沙眼?
Have you ever seen anyone with trachoma?
- 是的,我想是的 - 想事不关己不是那么容易的
- Yes, I suppose I have. - It's not that easy to remain uninvolved.
这边走
This way.
''事不关己不是那么容易的 ''
"Not that easy to remain uninvolved. "
我躲在打字机后太久了
I had hidden for so long behind a typewriter.
我们在 Phat Diem所见所闻
What we found there, what we saw, in Phat Diem.
那意味这什么?
What did that do?
他的热诚,我的冷漠?
To his zeal, to my detachment?
死人就事不关己了
The dead are not involved.
死人没有热诚
The dead have no zeal.
他们躺着等待
They are lying in wait.
你看见他们,他们的惨状
You see them, all their tenderness,
荤绕在你心头,挥之不去
and then they haunt you.
- 共产党人干的? - 这不是法国士兵干的
- Communists? - This is not the work of French soldiers.
这不合情理
It doesn't make sense.
共产党人不杀平民
The communists don't kill townspeople.
- 他们犯不着这样 - 也许是另一个党派干的
- It is not in their interest. - Maybe another faction.
这有那么多党派
There are so many of them.
每个党派都有自己的军队
Each with their own army.
你总在看的那本是什么书?
What's that book you're always reading?
约克.哈丁 民主的威胁
York Harding. The Dangers To Democracy.
- 美国作家? - 是的
- An American? - Yeah.
他在这儿呆了几年才回去
He was out here a couple of years back.
- 他呆了很久吗? - 我不知道
- Was he here long? - I don't know.
我听过他的一次演讲 乔见过他
I heard him lecture once. Joe actually met him.
他提出由第三方力量来控制越南
He put forward the idea of a third force to run Vietnam.
- 不是共产党,不是法国人 - 不是美国人?
- Not the communists and not the French. - Not the Americans?
不,我们可不是殖民主义者
No. We're not colonialists.
有时那反而能真得帮助这些人
Something that could really help these people.
- 你们谁有枪吗? - 没有
- You have a gun, either of you? - No.
他们今晚会进攻这里
They shall attack again tonight.
你不会想被活捉的
You don't want to be taken alive.
相信我
Believe me.
必要时自行了断吧
Shoot yourselves.
- 谢谢
- Thank you. - Thanks.
呆在碉堡里
Stay inside that bunker.
- 想吃点吗? - 不,谢谢
- Do you want something to eat? - No, thank you.
说吧
Come on.
你来这不是为了医疗队
You didn't come up to check your medical team.
乔.滕尼派你来的,是不是? 收信点情报
Joe Tunney sent you, right? A little intelligence work.
我总是藏不住秘密
I've never have been very good at keeping secrets.
我来这还有个原因
There is another reason why I came up here.
- 为了你 - 我?
- It's you. - Me?
是的
Yeah.
你说过你可能来这儿
You said that you might be coming up here.
我想说的是, 有关凤的
The thing is, it's about Phuong.
呃,从那晚我们第一次见面
Well, I guess it started that night when we were
在 Arc en Ciel,我和她跳舞
at the Arc en Ciel and I was dancing with her.
我不认为你们会有近一步关系
I didn't think you ever got close enough.
然后我和她还有她姐姐一起吃饭
And then I had dinner with her and her sister
那个周六...
that Saturday and...
当我坐在那儿看着她
just when I was sitting there looking at her,
一切在我看来都再清楚不过了
it all just became so clear to me.
我明白
I see.
听着,托马斯, 我不是有预谋这样的
Look, Tom, none of this was planned.
不可能...
There's no way...
我从不相信一见钟情
I never ever used to believe in love at first sight.
但是自从见到那可怕的地方的那些女子
But after seeing those other girls in that awful place
并且想到凤很可能变成她们中的一个
and thinking that Phuong could easily become one of them,
我想保护她
I want to protect her.
你想保护她时她怎么说?
What did she say when you offered her your protection?
- 我还没告诉她 - 你还没?
- I haven't told her yet. - You haven't?
没.我觉得那样不妥 我想先告诉你
No. I didn't think it would be right. I wanted to speak with you first.
听着,如果你们俩结婚了,那情况会完全不同
Look, if you two were married that would be completely different.
我不可能和她结婚 噢,该死!
I can never marry her. Oh, shit!
我妻子不可能同意离婚 她是天主教徒
My wife would never give me a divorce. She's a Catholic.
他们靠近了,他们开进来了
They're getting closer. They're walking in.
亲爱的托马斯 我想我会比你早回西贡
Dear Thomas - I guess I'll be back in Saigon ahead of you.
我再次向你保证
And I wanted to reassure you
直到你回来,我不会见凤
that I won't go to see Phuong until after you return.
如果你能赶上下一次出城 你将会在这周末回来
If you can make the next transport out, you should be back by the end of the week.
我会向你的助手打听你的消息
I can check in with your assistant to see if you made it.
如果你赶上了,我会在周五来见你
If so, I'll come around to see you both together on Friday.
5.00行吗?
Say 5. 00?
有人要去香港吗?
Anyone due to go out to Hong Kong?
我想路透社的人会去
Someone from Reuters, I believe.
把这个打出来,叫他帮我发到伦敦去
Type this up and ask him to cable it to London for me.
- 你的大新闻? - 是的
- Your big story? - Yes.
Phat Diem大屠杀 不知道谁干的
Massacre at Phat Diem. Nobody did it, of course.
不是法国人,不是共产党...
Not the French, not the communists...
只有各种谣传
But there are rumours.
- 怎么回事? - 我忘了这事了
- What's going on? - I forgot.
- 什么? - 是个集会
- What? - It's a rally.
- 一个新的政党 - 真见鬼
- A new political party. - Bloody hell.
我想还是把车留在这儿吧,先生 我们可以步行回去
I think I'd better leave your car here, sir. We can walk.
- 那不是泰上校吗? - 是将军
- lsn't that Colonel The? - General The.
- 谁升他为将军的? - 他自己
- Who made him a general? - He did.
他脱离法国人,自己组建了军队
He broke away from the French and formed his own army.
- 你好 - 嗨
- Hello. - Hi.
你有狗
You have a dog.
- 进来 - 谢谢
- Come in. - Thanks.
- 凤在哪? - 她去看她姐了
- Where's Phuong? - She's gone to see her sister.
- 想喝点威士忌吗? - 苏打水就行了,谢谢
- Would you like a whisky? - Just a soda, thanks.
他非得跳上床吗?
Does he have to do that?
公爵!到这儿来
Duke! Come here.
- 你叫他公爵? -  是的
- You called him Duke. - Yeah.
我在街上捡回来的
I found this guy in the street.
谁会不理睬这么可爱的狗呢?
Didn't l? Who could turn their back on a mug like that?
我在游行上看到你和乔.滕尼
I saw you and Joe Tunney at the parade.
你也去了集会?
Did you go on to the rally?
谢谢.是的,我去了 不过是为了别的事
Thanks. Yeah, I did. It was really something else.
我以为只有美国政客才爱搞那种无聊事
I thought only American politicians went in for that nonsense.
就差用来表示欢迎的彩带了
All that was missing was the ticker tape.
他们没忘军乐队伴奏
They sure didn't forget the brass band.
令人印象很深刻,那个泰将军
Impressive guy, that General The.
你不介意他是个彻头彻尾的自大狂吗?
It doesn't trouble you that he's a complete egomaniac?
听着,我不想在凤背后说她
Look, I don't want to talk about Phuong behind her back.
我以为她会在这儿,但...
I thought she was going to be here, but...
- 她姐姐跟我说了她的困境 - 什么困境?
- Her sister told me about her predicament. - And what predicament is that?
我以为你知道
I think you know.
你不能娶她
You can't marry her,
和你在一起,她永远不可能与越南人有正常的婚姻
and by living with you she can never have a proper marriage to a Vietnamese man.
她不需要同越南人有正常的婚姻
She doesn't need a proper marriage with a Vietnamese man.
她和我在一起
She's with me.
她来了
Here she is.
你好,凤
Hello, Phuong.
我姐出去了
My sister is out.
- 你好 - 你好,很高兴见到你
- Hello. - Hello. It's nice to see you.
派尔先生是特地来看你的,凤
It's you that Mr Pyle has come to visit, Phuong.
为什么我们不坐下呢?
So why don't we all sit down?
除非你想我离开
Unless, of course, you want me to leave.
不,那不妥
No. That wouldn't be right.
那我们坐下吧
We should sit down, then.
说吧
Fire away.
自从我见到你,同你跳舞,和你聊天
Ever since I met you and danced with you and talked with you,
我无时无刻不想着你
I haven't been able to get you out of my thoughts for more than a moment.
我已经爱上你了
I've fallen in love with you.
你爱上我?
You fall in love with me?
请相信我 我以前从没这样过
Please believe me. I've never behaved like this before.
我很抱歉,这很唐突,不太礼貌,但...
I apologise. It is abrupt and it is ill-mannered, but...
我爱你
I'm in love with you.
你不该是单膝下跪的吗?
Shouldn't you be on one knee?
凤,我不是个富有的人
Look... Phuong, I'm not a rich man
但我有我的资产
but I do have assets.
-我们来丢硬币决定吧 - 你能给她什么?
- Let's toss for her. - What can you offer her?
- 噢,主啊 - 我不奢望你立刻爱上我
- Oh, Christ. - I don't expect you to love me right away.
你总是和司机上床
You could always make love to the chauffeur.
你没有权利侮辱她!
You have no right to insult her!
- 让你那该死的狗闭上嘴 - 跟我走吧
- Shut your bloody dog up. - Come away with me.
叫他走,带上他的狗
Tell him to bugger off and take his dog with him.
不
No.
你说不?
Did you say no?
坐下喝几杯吧
Yes. Sit down and have a scotch.
不,我该走了,我很抱歉
No. I should go. I'm so sorry.
- 你想抽烟斗吗? - 烟斗?
- Do you want to smoke a pipe? - A pipe?
鸦片
Opium.
不,我干嘛要抽那个?
No. Why would I do that?
我知道我们结婚前你就警告过我
I know before we married you warned me
你的信仰决定了你不可能和我离婚
beliefs meant that there could never be a divorce.
但我还是想请求你
All the same, that's what I'm asking for now.
事实上,我深深地爱着另一个人
The fact is, I love someone very much.
我期望你好好想想再答复我
I want you to feel affection and act before you have time to think.
发电报告诉我你同意吧
Just cable and tell me you agree.
我刚写信请求我妻子和我离婚
I've just asked my wife for a divorce.
你姐姐...
Your sister...
她真的不在?
Was she really out?
我说了她不在
I told you.
我以为也许她叫你回来
I thought perhaps she sent you back
这样你就可以遇见派尔
so that you could meet Pyle.
他是那么年青
He's very young.
那并不重要
That's not so important.
好消息.他们登了你的报道
Good news. They printed your story.
我收到史达明的电报 他们让我再留一个月
I got a cable from Stemins. This got me a month's reprieve.
第十页 ''法军突破共军包围.''
Page ten. "French Break Communist Siege."
他们没全用我的报道,不是吗?
They didn't use much, did they?
根本没提到村民被杀
Nothing here about the villagers that were killed.
法国报纸怎么说?
What did the French papers say?
头条当然是谴责共军
Headlines blame it on the communists, of course.
好吧,一个月就一个月
Well, a month is a month.
你还能告诉我什么有关这个泰将军的?
What else can you tell me about this General The?
他既反对法军,也反对共军
He's set himself up against both the French and the communists.
你认为他会接受我的采访吗?
Do you think he'd give me an interview if I went up there?
很难说
Difficult to say.
也许他认为他能有机会散布他的主张
Perhaps if he thought he could get his message across.
问题是怎么通过关卡
The problem would be getting it past the censor.
不,真正的问题是怎样在天黑前...
No, the real problem would be to get close to the Cambodian border
通过柬埔寨边境
and back before dark.
共军晚上控制了公路
The communists control that road at night.
很多欧洲人在那儿被杀
So many Europeans have been killed out there.
我是伦敦时报的托马斯.福勒
I am Thomas Fowler of the London Times
我来这采访泰将军
and I'm here to interview General The.
我是伦敦时报的托马斯.福勒
I'm Thomas Fowler of the London Times.
我来这采访泰将军
I'm here to see General The.
九月,十月,十一月...
September, October, November...
派尔向凤未婚后我只见过他一次
I'd seen Pyle only once since he'd asked Phuong to marry him,
在欧洲旅馆
at the Continental.
当然,他很客气 -
He'd been polite, of course -
问我怎样,凤怎样?
how was I, how was Phuong?
他说他很忙,不在城里
He'd been busy, he said, out of the city,
在忙他的医疗计划
working on his medical programme.
不过不知何故,我并不讶异见到他
Though somehow, I wasn't surprised to see him.
我讶异的是我很高兴见到他
I was surprised to be pleased to see him.
- 什么风把你吹到这儿来了? - 我想采访泰将军
- What brings you out to these parts? - I was hoping to interview the General.
但他们不让我进去
But they've thrown me out of the place.
- 你这次又有什么借口? - 这就像是对我们的测试
- What's your excuse this time? - This is like a test run for us.
法国人,以他们典型的法国伤风 非常不合作
The French, in their typically French way, have been very uncooperative
但泰将军却不错 让我们在这儿扎营
but General The has been good enough to let us set up camp here.
我让他们放你进去
I'll get them to let you in.
乔.滕尼同与泰亲近的商人进行援助计划
Joe Tunney's running aid programmes with business people close to The.
- 莫依先生 - 派乐先生
- Mr Muoi. - Mr Pyle.
- 你好,你怎样? - 很好
- Hello. How are you? - Good.
我姓莫依 泰将军只有几分钟时间
My name is Mr Muoi. The General only has a few moments.
我能先问你一个问题吗?
May I first ask you a question?
-请 - 你和泰将军是什么关系?
- Please. - What is your relationship to the General?
我是生意人,也是爱国者
I'm a businessman and a patriot.
你看到的这些供给和援助 很多都是我努力的结果
Many of the supplies and aid you see are the result of my efforts.
可以开始了吗?
Shall we begin?
你说你已脱离了
You say you've broken away from
你所服役的法军和越军
the French and Vietnamese forces with which you serve.
你们之间还有关系吗?
Do any ties remain?
法国人是殖民主义者
The French are colonialists.
不值得信任
Not to be trusted.
应该由独立的越南人来管理这国家
It will take an independent Vietnamese leader to rule our country.
只有这么少的供给和士兵
How does the General expect to launch a successful campaign
将军你凭什么...
against the larger forces of the communists and the French
打赢法军和共军大部队?
with so few men and supplies?
谁为将军提供致胜手段?
And who is providing the means for the General to achieve this?
他是否在北部作战?
Has he been fighting his war in the north?
在Phat Diem有场大屠杀
There was a massacre at Phat Diem.
你的军队是不是在那儿?
Were your forces present?
很遗憾,将军突然想起有个紧急约见
Regrettably the General has just recalled that he has an urgent appointment.
- 所以,请了 - 谢谢
- So, please. - Thank you.
这么快
That was quick.
事情不像我计划的那样
Things didn't go entirely according to plan.
小心乔
Watch yourself with Joe.
我觉得他和泰将军在搞鬼
I think he's up to something with General The.
我能坐你的车回西贡吗? 我的车有点问题
Can I get a ride to Saigon with you? Something's wrong with my car.
可以,当然可以
Yes, of course you can.
看,有好心人帮我擦车
Hello. Some kind soul has had mine cleaned.
我听说你将被召会伦敦
I heard a rumour that you'd been recalled to London.
真的?谁告诉你的?
Really? Who told you that?
凤的姐姐
Phuong's sister.
- 妈的 - 怎么了?
- Shit. - What is it?
没油了
We're out of petrol.
刚才肯定有谁把油吸走了
Some bugger up in the mountains must have siphoned it off.
也许他们在了望塔有备用油
They might have some spare petrol in that watchtower.
看上去是废弃的塔
It looks like it's deserted.
我进去看看
I'll go in and have a look.
有人吗?
Hello?
- 没事吧? - 上来
- Is everything OK? - Come up.
我和我朋友不得不在这呆到早上了
这是不允许的
是我朋友
没事的,请放下枪
请放下枪,他是我朋友
在想什么?
What are you thinking?
在想凤现在在做什么
I was wondering what she was doing right now.
今天早上她和朋友一起早茶
This morning she met her friends for elevenses
在 La Fontaine.
at La Fontaine.
吃冰淇淋,聊近来的闲话
Ice cream and the latest gossip.
回家路上,她去了市集
On her way home she stopped at the market
买鱼做午餐
for fresh fish for dinner.
现在她在翻杂志
And now she's flipping through the pages of magazines
看皇室成员和电影明星的照片
Iooking at photographs of the royal family and film stars,
听巴赫的曲子
Iistening to Bach's Well-Tempered Clavier.
我和她就是从巴赫开始的
I just got her started on Bach.
你有过很多女人吗,托马斯?
Have you had a lot of women, Thomas?
开始时很滥交
You start out by being promiscuous,
但最后你会很专一 -
and end up like your grandfather -
对一个女人忠诚不二
faithful to one woman.
我知道凤不是没我就不行
I know I'm not essential to Phuong.
但你相信我
But believe me when I tell you that
如果我失去她
if I were to lose her,
对我而言...
for me...
就是死亡的开始
it would be the beginning of death.
有人来了
Somebody's had it.
从这到西贡有30或40个了望塔
There are 30 or 40 of these towers between here and Saigon.
他们一晚只袭击一到两个 所以我们的机率不是很大
They only hit one or two a night so our odds aren't too bad.
那你觉得共军来袭时他们会怎样?
So what do you think they'd do if the communists attacked?
这两个人? 他们会开火然后逃跑
These two? They'd fire a shot and run.
他们为什么要为我们而死? 或为法国人
Why should they die for us? Or the French.
那是什么? 我看见有东西在动
What's that? I thought I saw something move.
天啊,他们在这儿!
Christ, they're here!
就我所听懂的 他们叫我们投降
As far as I can make out, he told them to give us up or else.
别动! 给我枪!
Stop! Give me that!
快来,托马斯
Come on, Thomas.
- 怎么了? - 我想我扭到脚了
- What is it? - I think I've twisted my ankle.
我沿路去下一个塔
I'm gonna head up the road to the next watchtower.
看看能不能找到点汽油
See if I can find a French patrol.
坐好,我会回来的
Sit tight, OK? I'll be back.
能自我介绍吗?我叫托马斯. 福勒
May I introduce myself? Thomas Fowler.
我找到汽油了
I found a patrol.
如果我死了...
If I had died...
你就能和她一起了
you could have had her.
我想你得通知你的情报员
And I think you should inform your sources
泰将军手下可不止他们所说的几百个人
that General The has a lot more men than the hundred of their count.
我们得认真考虑他的报道
He's a story we should take seriously.
别低估了爱国者,先生
Never underestimate a patriot, sir.
你了解莫依吗? 他怎么能资助军队?
What do you know about Muoi? Could he finance The's army?
他有家自行车厂!
He owns a bicycle factory!
我想乔.滕尼和泰有阴谋
Well, I think Joe Tunney is plotting with he and The.
他不止在搞外国援助这么简单
And it's more than just foreign aid programmes.
我看看我能有什么消息,先生
I'll see what I can find out, sir.
办公室一切都井井有条
Things are under control at the office.
- 多休息休息吧 - 谢谢,辛
- Try to get some rest. - Thank you, Hinh.
我好想你
I missed you.
- 你还好吧? - 骨头还没散
- Are you all right? - I'm all in one piece.
- 有封伦敦来的信 - 是吗?
- You got a letter from London. - Yes?
- 我帮你拿? - 不,亲亲我
- I fetch it for you? - No. Give me a kiss.
再亲
Big one.
我来拿
I will get it.
你看起来很害怕
You look afraid.
我想我最好还是喝点白兰地
I think I'd better have a brandy and soda.
派尔,进来,进来
Pyle. Come in, come in.
我想顺便过来看看你怎样
Thought I'd drop by and see how you were doing.
- 我很好,谢谢 - 腿怎样?
- Very well, thanks. - How's the leg?
不能打网球了 不过我本来就不会打
My tennis game will suffer, but it wasn't much to begin with.
谢谢
Thank you.
我很高兴你能来
I'm glad you dropped by.
我们得谢谢派尔先生 他救了我的命
We have to thank Mr Pyle, Phuong, for saving my life.
谢谢
Thank you.
你姐姐怎样?
How's your sister doing?
- 姐姐? - 是的
- Sister? - Yes.
艾登为她找了份工作,为美国人做事
Alden got her a job with Americans.
噢,是吗?
Oh, yes?
她很喜欢那工作,谢谢
She likes it very much. Thank you.
好的,我很高兴
Good. I'm very glad.
既然你们俩都在这儿
Since you're both here, now is as good a time as any
我收到我妻子的信
to tell you that I have received a letter from my wife
她同意和我离婚了
and she has more or less agreed to give me a divorce.
那太好了
That's wonderful.
- 过来坐 - 谢谢,我还有事儿
- Come sit. - Thank you. I've got plans.
感谢到访
Thank you for dropping by.
再见
Bye.
先生,我...
Sir, l...
我信任你,托马斯
I trusted you, Thomas.
有女人在就有麻烦
Always a mistake when there's a woman involved.
你不用谎言就不可能赢我?
Couldn't you have won without lying?
怎么了,到底?
What is it, anyway?
我姐姐看了你妻子的信
My sister read the letter from your wife.
我给她看的
I show it to her
因为...我太自豪了
because... I was so proud.
- 太高兴了 - 你怎么能这样欺骗她?
- So happy. - How could you treat her like this?
''亲爱的托马斯- 你身边总是有女人
"Dear Thomas - you always picked up women
就像你的鞋总粘到泥一样''
Iike you picked up mud on your shoes."
我很抱歉,凤
I'm sorry, Phuong.
- 那你为什么要骗她? - 很明显因为我想留住她
- So then why'd you lie to her? - Because I wanted to keep her.
那不是爱
That's not love.
看到吧,他甚至都不否认自己是个骗子
''你难道没想过当你离开她回英国她会有多寂寞吗?''
"Have you ever stopped to think how lonely she'll be in England when you leave her?"
闭嘴,看在老天的份上
Shut up, for Christ's sake.
''我不主张离婚''
"l don't believe in divorce."
''我的信仰也不允许 因此答案还是
"My religion forbids it. And so the answer is
不.''
no."
我被教育别看人家的信
I was taught never to read other people's letters.
- 我被教育别说谎 - 走吧,凤
- I was taught not to tell lies. - Come on, Phuong.
我不说越南话
I don't speak Vietnamese.
滚吧
Get lost.
你是对的,莫依的确有关系网
You were right about Muoi. He does have connections.
呆会再谈这个好吗?
Can we discuss this some other time?
外国板条箱通过他的厂进来
Crates from overseas have been moving through his factory,
绕过法国海关
bypassing French customs.
我的情报员不知道箱里装的是什么
My sources have been unable to determine what they contain.
他很可能贿赂了什么人
He's probably got someone on the take.
他是出口商,不是进口商
He's an exporter, not an importer.
好的,我们明天再查好吗?
Yes, well, we'll do that tomorrow, OK?
不,今天下午就要出货了
No. A shipment just came in this afternoon.
明早就运走了
It could be gone by the morning.
- Diolacton是什么? - 我们得马上走
- What is this Diolacton? - We must leave immediately.
这英国人疯了,他喝太多了
回家去吧,回家
他什么也不是
- 你在干什么? - 在救你的命,快走!
- What are you doing? - Trying to save your life. Go!
早上好
Good morning.
- 我能为你做什么? -你已经做了够多了
- Can I help you? - You've done quite enough already.
- 派尔在哪? - 他今天上午不在这
- Where's Pyle? - He's not in the office this morning.
- 他很多事在家做 - 我知道他在家做什么
- He does a lot of work at home. - I know what he does at home.
- 你什么意思? - 问她,她把我的女人和他配了队
- What do you mean? - Ask her. She's fixed him up with my girl.
- 你不能在办公室生事 -  我知道这样很粗鲁
- We can't have scenes in the office. - I know I am behaving badly.
但我有充分理由粗鲁
But I have every intention of behaving badly.
谁在这种情况下都会发火
This is exactly the kind of situation where one should behave badly.
- 你能声音小一点吗? -  你干嘛不滚开?
- Could we please lower our voices? - Why don't you bugger off?
托马斯,这儿有女士
Thomas, there is a lady here.
我和这个女士很熟
This lady and I know each other quite well.
她本来想从我身上捞油水 现在她从派尔那捞
She tried to get a rake-off from me, but now she's getting one from Pyle.
- 我们有很多事要做 -  如果派尔打电话来,跟他说我来过
- We have a lot of work to do. - If Pyle phones, tell him I called.
他应该回访
It would be polite to return the visit.
他怎么进来的?
How did he get in here?
这是波士顿吗?
This is Boston?
不,这是尼加拉瀑布.这也是
No, that's Niagara Falls. So is that.
这是波士顿,那是法纳尔大厅
This is Boston. That's Faneuil Hall.
我等不及想带你回祖国
I can't wait to take you to my country.
我学校里的朋友
My friend from school.
她和男友去机场
She go to airport with her boyfriend.
他说要带她去法国
He said he'd take her to France.
但在机场
But in the airport,
他不见了,留她一人在那儿
he disappear, leave her there.
很多交了法国男友的女孩
So many girls with French boyfriend,
没一个嫁过去
no one to marry them.
我不会那样对你
Well, that'll never happen to you.
我保证
I promise.
- 嗨 - 圣诞节过得好吗?
- Hi. - Have a nice Christmas?
有派队
One long party.
凤忘了什么吗?
Did Phuong forget something?
听说你来过公使馆
Heard you came by the legation.
是的
Yes.
- 那是谁? - 保镖.我们现在都有保镖
- Who's this? - Bodyguard. We all have them now.
结婚了吗?
Are you married yet?
没,我想等我们有了房子才合适
No, I figured I'd wait until we got home and do it properly.
你不介意"不合适地"住在这儿?
You don't mind living here improperly?
如果你总这么讽刺 那很难和你谈话
It's hard to talk if you're going to be so cynical.
我意思是最好我父母在场
I meant it'd be good to do it with my parents there.
总部给我发电报,要我回去
I had a cable from head office. They want me back.
噢,那...
Oh, that's...
所以凤跟随你是件好事
So it's good that Phuong went off with you.
要不然她会变成格兰吉的下一个女人
She might have ended up as another piece of arse for someone like Granger.
至少我知道你对她不错
At least I know you'll treat her right.
那我们是不是还是朋友?
So does this mean that we can still be friends?
为什么不是
I don't see why not.
什么是Diolacton?
So what is Diolacton, anyway?
- 你知道那个? - 我不该知道吗?
- You know about that? - Shouldn't l?
呃... Diolacton 是一种塑胶
Well... Diolacton is a milk-based plastic.
用来做眼镜架
It's used for the frames in the eyeglasses.
你还和泰将军有联系吗?
Are you still in touch with General The?
- 我们一直敞开大门 - 那莫依呢?
- We keep the channels open. - And Muoi?
莫依先生帮助我们把供给送过海关
Mr Muoi's helped get our supplies through customs.
- 法国人开始收费了... - 你曾向我要建议
- The French have started to charge for... - You asked me for advice once.
我的建议是,把那该死的第三方力量留给乔去办
Here it is. Leave the bloody third force to Joe,
忘了你的约克.哈丁 带凤回家去吧
forget York Harding, and go home with Phuong.
请你关上门走吧,好吗?
And would you shut the door on the way out, please?
拉里,早上好,今天干什么?
Morning, Larry. What is it today?
一些麻烦的任务
You know, some cockamamie assignment.
我们得走了 乔.滕尼说得在11点10分到这儿
We should go. Joe Tunney said to be out of here by ten to eleven.
- 什么事,到底? - 我不清楚
- What is it, anyway? - I'm not sure.
- 是示威吗? - 不知道
- Is it a demonstration? - I don't know.
我朋友在这儿
My friend is in there.
你手破了吗,先生?
Did you cut your hand, sir?
是的
Yes.
- 那儿情况怎样? - 死了30人
- How is it down there? - 30 dead.
也许到明早还要死20人
Probably 20 more by morning.
他们开始逮捕共产党拥护者
They've started arresting communist sympathisers.
那儿有个女人
There was a woman.
抱着孩子
With a baby.
她用帽子盖住孩子
She covered it with her hat.
一个男人...死了
This man... he died.
死在家人面前
Right in front of his family.
派尔...
Pyle...
你看见他了?
Did you see him?
他会说越南话
He spoke Vietnamese.
说得像...母语那么好
Like... Iike it was his, you know, native language.
默里!过来!拍这个
Murray! Come over here! Get this.
快,这边
Move it. Right here. On this side.
懂了吗? 到别的地方帮忙去
Understand? Go make yourself useful somewhere else.
Diolacton 是一种塑胶 用来做眼镜架
Diolacton is a milk-based plastic. We used it for the frames.
- 一共发了几篇稿? - 今年?
- How many stories have we given them? - This year?
''酪蛋白塑胶''
"Casein plastics."
''从牛乳蛋白质中提取''
"Made from milk protein."
约克.哈丁:"民主的威胁" 他提出由第三方....
York Harding: "Dangers to Democracy. " He put forward the idea of a third force...
''用于制造工业龟甲和玉''
"Used in the manufacture of imitation tortoiseshell and jade."
''商品名: Diolacton.''
"Trade name: Diolacton."
''也用做爆炸物中的
"Also used as a plasticiser
可塑剂''
in explosive compounds."
乔.滕尼在同泰亲近的商人做援助计划
Joe Tunney's running aid programmes with business people close to The.
莫依
Muoi.
和泰
And The.
应该由独立的越南人来统治越南
It will take an independent Vietnamese leader to rule our country.
美国人在为他们提供
The Americans have been supplying them
做炸弹的材料
with materials to make bombs.
福勒到处都有同谋
Fowler sees conspiracies everywhere.
我有线人想和你的朋友谈谈
I have some contacts who would like to speak to your friend.
乔.滕尼?
Joe T unney?
派尔?
Pyle?
他们认为他能提供有关这一切的重要情报
They feel he can give them important information about all this.
你是说派尔是美国战略情报局的?
You're saying Pyle is OSS?
我想现在叫中情局
I believe the new name is the ClA.
- 每个人都能和他谈话 - 并不那么容易
- Anyone could speak to him. - It's not so easy.
他有保镖跟着
He's followed by protectors.
但如果你要求和他单独见面
But if you asked to meet with him, man to man,
他会一个人来的
he would come along.
你的线人,是共产党人吗?
These contacts. Are they communist?
公开时,不是 私底下,是
Officially, no. Unofficially, yes.
我不知道
I don't know.
假设你请他去Vieux Moulin吃晚饭
Suppose you invite him to dinner at the Vieux Moulin,
在9.00 到9.30之间
say between 9.00 and 9.30.
在那附近,我朋友可以不受干扰的同他谈谈
It's quiet near there. My friends can speak to him undisturbed.
也许他没空
Maybe he's engaged.
6.30我的联络人会派人到你公寓外的街口
At 6.30, my contacts will have someone in the street outside your apartment.
你只要决定请不请他吃晚饭...
All you have to do, if you decide to invite him to dinner...
如果请,就到窗口打开一本书
go to the window and open a book.
他们会对他怎样?
What will they do to him?
我保证,我的联络人会视乎情况尽量和气
I promise you - my contacts will act as gently as the situation allows.
福勒先生,
Sooner or later, Mr Fowler,
你迟早要选择拥护某方
one has to take sides
只要你还有人性
if one is to remain human.
我想和你谈谈今早发生的事
I need to speak to you about what happened this morning
在Place Garnier.
in the Place Garnier.
- 凤 - 你的信
- Phuong. - A letter for you.
谢谢
Thank you.
给我几分钟好吗?
Just give me a few minutes, all right?
进来
Come in.
我收到你的条子
I got your message.
我知道
So I see.
- 我想喝一杯 - 我只有烈酒
- I'd love a drink. - I've only got hard liquor.
也许你在当值 我注意到你最近很少休息
You're probably on duty. I've noticed you're rarely off duty these days.
威士忌酒.人总会改变
Whisky'd be fine. People change.
或者一个人并不是我们以为的那样
Or maybe they just never were what we thought they were.
你在说谁,托马斯?我还是你?
Who of us is, Thomas? Who of us is?
我猜你想谈泰将军?
You want to talk about General The?
是的,还有莫依先生
Yes. And Mr Muoi.
还有Diolacton.
And Diolacton.
- 我们今天下午见过面 - 他在西贡?
- We met with The this afternoon. - He's in Saigon?
他来看爆炸的情况?
Come to see how his explosives worked?
他原本和目标是军事游行
His original target was a military parade.
我不该告诉你这个 我们对他很强硬
We were pretty tough on him.
你告诉他你们不会支持他了?
Did you tell him you wouldn't support him?
- 我们告诉他如果他在行差踏错... - 他想杀了你,在你去西贡的路上
- We told him if he steps out of line again... - He tried to kill you on the road to Saigon.
不,他想杀的是你
No. He tried to kill you.
你早知道?
You knew?
我怀疑他或他的手下要搞什么动作
I suspected that he might try something. Or one of his officers.
所以我跟踪他们以防万一
So I tagged along just in case.
如果你以为你能控制泰将军 那你真是傻瓜一个
You're a fool if you think you can control General The.
在战争中,你得利用你能利用的工具
In a war, you use the tools you've got.
目前来讲,他是我们能利用的最好工具
Right now, he's the best we have.
就算与此同时会有更多人得死去
And in the meantime, even more people must die.
去年美国向印度支那的法军
Last year the US government gave $21 0 million
提供了2亿1千万军事援助
in military assistance to the French in lndochina.
如果我们要遏制共产主义 支持第三方
If we are going to stop communism and underwrite a third way,
我们必需得找个人民崇拜的领袖
we need to give the people a leader who they admire.
明早国会听到报告,看过共产党暴行的照片
Tomorrow when Congress reads the sees the photographs
他们会支持我们的计划的
of the communist atrocities, they are going to give us that support.
法国人不会遏制共产主义
The French won't stop the communists.
他们没大脑,不懂得内情
They haven't got the brains and they haven't got the guts.
我与这事有什么关系?
How did I fit into all this?
我是你身份掩饰的一部分?
Am I part of your cover?
还是情报来源?
Or a source of information?
还是你一直都盯上凤?
Or did you have your eye on Phuong all the time?
你和凤? 我从未预谋过什么 相信我
You and Phuong? I never planned for any of that to happen. Believe me.
如果我没遇到你或她,事情会更好办些
It would have been easier if I'd never met either one of you.
- 但你遇到了,所以你向我们说谎 - 你想我跟你说什么?
- But you did. And you lied to us. - What do you want me to tell you?
说我没参与行动? 没参与计划?
That I took no action? That I have no opinion?
告诉我你不是故意让这些发生
Tell me that you don't mean any of this.
告诉我你只是听从命令
Tell me that you were only obeying orders.
或告诉我在你看到广场爆炸中的...
Or tell me that after what you saw in the square, those children,
无辜的,对人没有任何威胁的孩子后
who did nothing and hurt no one,
对于这个行动的残暴和荒唐
tell me that you were so confused and horrified
你是那么的困惑,惊恐
at how brutal and insane these actions are.
告诉我你对凤的爱使你对这一切产生疑问
Tell me how your love for Phuong has caused you to have some doubts.
但正因为凤,我更加坚定
But it's because of Phuong that I am even more determined.
就说凤吧 她是美人,是教授的女儿
Let's just look at Phuong. There's beauty. There's daughter of a professor.
是舞女,是欧洲老男人的情妇
Taxi dancer. Mistress of an older European man.
那些都充分反映这整个国家
That pretty well describes the whole country.
听着,托马斯,我们到这就是要把越南 从那一切中解脱出来
Look, Thomas, we are here to save Vietnam from all of that.
广场上发生的事令我觉得不舒服
What happened in the square makes me sick.
但长远来看,我在拯救生命
But in the long run, I'm going to save lives.
那人是你,是不是?
It's you, isn't it?
乔.滕尼,公使馆的人
Joe Tunney, the staff at the legation,
莫依,泰将军
Mr Muoi, General The.
他们都他妈的听人的命令,派尔
They all take their fucking orders from you, Pyle.
约克.哈丁在你随身带的那书里胡说八道 什么第三方力量
York Harding prattles on about a third force in that book you carry around.
而你却真得策划了一个
You've actually gone out and made one.
我不认为你领会到了全局观念,托马斯
I don't think you see the big picture, Thomas.
不,我领会到了
No, I do not see the big picture.
你知道这首诗吗?
Do you know this poem?
''我走在街上,什么也不在乎
"l walk down the street and I don't give a damn
人们看着我,问我我是谁
The people, they stare and they ask who I am
如果不巧我撞到个无赖
And if by chance I should run over a cad
我会赔偿,如果情况不是太坏''
I can pay for the damage, if ever so bad."
就算有分歧我们也还是朋友,是吗,托马斯?
We can disagree and remain friends, can't we, Thomas?
当然
Yes.
我很抱歉
Look, I'm sorry.
我们去吃饭吧 这些事都丢一边吧
Let's have dinner and put all this mess behind us.
- 9.00, 在Vieux Moulin见,好吗? - 听上去不错
- 9.00, Vieux Moulin. OK? - That sounds great.
我很期待我们的谈话
I miss our conversations.
是Vieux Moulin
Vieux Moulin it is.
好吧,那我叫凤和她姐姐吃饭
All right, then. I'll tell Phuong she can have dinner with her sister.
我叫她吃完饭来见我
I'll get her to meet me here afterwards.
如果你不认识,直接来这儿
Look, if you can't make it, come straight here.
- 我会等你的 - 好的
- I'll wait for you. - All right.
一会见,托马斯
I'll see you soon, Thomas.
走
Walk.
我得跟会说英语的人聊聊
I need to talk to somebody who speaks English.
你知道吗,今晚是我儿子的生日
You see, it's my son's birthday tonight.
我们要问你几个问题
We need to ask you some questions.
我是美国公使馆的 我只是帮人治眼睛的
I'm from the American legation. I just try and help people see.
但问题是...
The thing is, l...
我收到妻子的电报
I got a cable from my wife.
我儿子得了小儿麻痹 他们不知道他挺不挺得过去
My boy has polio. They don't know if he's going to make it.
我不介意他残废
I don't care if he's crippled.
只要他别死
I just don't want him to die.
我很抱歉,我得去透透气
I'm sorry. I've just got to get some air.
至少2000人死亡,还有更多受伤
At least 2,000 people were killed and scores of others injured.
上星期在西贡的爆炸事件中
In the wake of last week's bomb blast in Saigon,
法国官方报道...
French officials report...
很抱歉打扰你,但...
I'm sorry to bother you, but...
你介意和我一起下楼吗?
would you mind to come downstairs with me?
- 你想怎样? - 我要给你看点东西
- What do you want? - I have something to show you.
似乎派尔先生死那晚来见过你
It seems Monsieur Pyle came to see you the night he died.
- 那又怎样? - 你说他没来过
- So what, Vigot? - You said he did not.
还有,我们找到派尔的狗
By the way, we found Pyle's dog.
他们割段了他的喉咙
They cut its throat.
你看到吗?
You see here?
派尔的狗脚趾间有水泥
Pyle's dog had cement between its toes.
这的水泥是他被杀那天下午浇得
This was poured on the afternoon of his murder.
那能说明什么?
So what does that prove?
还有Vieux Moulin 饭店的老板告诉我
And the patron of the Vieux Moulin told me
那晚你只要了一个位子
that night you asked for a table for one.
而不是两个
Not two.
我对于我最初的口供没任何可再说的
I have nothing more to add to my original statement.
没有?
Nothing?
你知道不是我杀他的
You know I didn't kill him, Vigot.
现在是战争年代
There's a war on.
每天都有人死
People are dying every day.
找别的女孩
Ask another girl.
我不想找别的女孩
I don't want another girl.
你能回到我身边吗,凤?
Will you come back now, Phuong?
- 你能回到我身边吗? - 回伦敦?
- Will you come back to me? - To London?
不,不回伦敦
No. Not to London.
那我不会回来的
Then I don't come back.
拜托,我...
Please. I...
我不能带你去伦敦
I can't take you to London.
因为我不去那儿
Because I'm not going.
我不会离开你
I'm not leaving you.
永远不
Never.
你能回来我身边吗?
Will you come back to me?
- 能帮我拆头发吗? - 好的
- Will you take down my hair? - Yes.
你想他吗?
Do you miss him?
是的
Yes.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
为什么抱歉?
Why are you sorry?
我不知道
I don't know.
我只是觉得...
I just feel that...
我应该向....谁道歉
I ought to apologise to... someone.
不是我
Not to me.
永远不会是我
Never to me.
人们说你来到越南
They say you come to Vietnam
你会立即明白很多事
and understand a lot in a few minutes.
剩下的得自己去体验
The rest has got to be lived.
他们说不管你寻求什么
They say whatever it was you were looking for
你都能在这如愿以偿
you will find here.
人们说每间房里都有鬼魂
They say there is a ghost in every house.
如果你能和他和平共处
And if you can make peace with him,
他会很安静
he will stay quiet.